<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Patrick Blanchenay (U of Toronto)</title><link>https://pblanchenay.github.io/</link><atom:link href="https://pblanchenay.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Patrick Blanchenay (U of Toronto)</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://pblanchenay.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url><title>Patrick Blanchenay (U of Toronto)</title><link>https://pblanchenay.github.io/</link></image><item><title>Academic references</title><link>https://pblanchenay.github.io/academicreferences/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pblanchenay.github.io/academicreferences/</guid><description>&lt;p>I am in general happy to write a reference letter for former students who have done well in my courses (ranking in the top 20%); however, it takes time. To make sure you know what you are asking, and whether it would actually help your application, here is some guidance. Please read in full.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-are-reference-letters-for-what-would-it-contain">What are reference letters for? What would it contain?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Selection committees are usually interested in admitting students who have the skills and motivation to succeed in the program. The goal of a reference letter is to provide accurate information about you to that selection committee. (It is not to get you into the program at all costs.)&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In any reference letter I will, at the minimum, mention the grade you received in my course, and how it compares to other students, current and past.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I will also provide any type of information that I deemed relevant for the committee, elements that indicate how well you would do in the program, how motivated you are, how much you would benefit from the program, and how the program would benefit to have you as a student.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I do not lie and I try to be honest and objective.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reference letters are confidential between myself and the selection committee.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="should-you-ask-me-for-a-reference-letter">Should you ask me for a reference letter?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A reference letter will increase your chances if it can provide information about you that is 1/ positive, 2/ specific and credible, and 3/ relevant to the program you are applying to.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>You should have done particularly well in my course, and appear &lt;strong>motivated&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Usually that means ranking in the top 20% of students who took that course with me. Depending on the course that could mean an 78/100, or a 90/100. If you&amp;rsquo;re unsure, you can ask.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I will also have a look at your other course grades to see if your performance in my course is a fluke or if you are doing generally well.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you didn&amp;rsquo;t do really well in my course, it really is in your interest to ask instead the instructor of a course you did particularly well in. A letter about an average performance will HARM your application.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>I should be able to provide information that is &lt;strong>specific&lt;/strong> and would stand out to a selection committee.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In any given course, I typically teach between 180 and 350 students per session. Did you come regularly to office hours? Did we have any meaningful interactions?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the only thing I know about you are your grades, the letter cannot be very specific or informative; it is going to be very generic and has little chance of helping your application. It might be in your interest to ask another instructor who knows you better.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>I should be able to comment on aspects of your application that are &lt;strong>relevant&lt;/strong> for the program you are applying to.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Is the course you took with me relevant for the program? Does it highlight some ability of yours that would help you succeed in the program?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you are applying to a program that is totally unrelated to the course you took with me, it is harder to make my letter relevant to the selection committee. Are there particular skills you acquired in my course that would be useful for &lt;em>that particular program&lt;/em>? You might be better off asking an instructor that can comment on the skills/topics that are particularly relevant for that program.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="am-i-willing-to-write-a-letter-for-you">Am I willing to write a letter for you?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In general yes if you did well in my course (ranking in the top 20%), but I reserve the right to refuse writing a letter for you (i.e. it&amp;rsquo;s not guaranteed).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I refuse it is usually for one of these reasons:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I believe it would not help your application (see the 3 points above).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I believe your application is not fit for a particular program (e.g. you scored in top 25% in my course and are applying to a very selective program).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I do not have enough time before the deadline. &lt;strong>Allow 3 weeks before the nearest deadline.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you have never &lt;em>completed&lt;/em> a course with me, I am in general very reluctant to write for you. If you are a current student, I can only write if I have sufficient info about you, which is rare for current students.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="you-have-read-all-this-and-would-like-me-to-write-a-letter-what-should-you-do">You have read all this and would like me to write a letter. What should you do?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Make sure to contact me well in advance of deadlines. Most postgraduate programs have deadlines between early December to early February.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Allow three weeks before the earliest deadline.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Be ready to meet for a quick chat about your applications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Contact me by email (not in office hours).
&lt;strong>Your email should contain:&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Your name &amp;amp; student ID.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> The following Excel file, renamed appropriately, filled in with the list of applications for which you want my reference letter: &lt;a href="../files/NAME_FirstName_Programs_ApplicationLists.xlsx">NAME_FirstName_Programs_ApplicationLists.xlsx&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> A full up-to-date UofT academic transcript.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> An up-to-date CV.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Any document (e.g. cover letter) that you wish to supply to the application process.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-i-will-not-do-for-you">What I will not do for you&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Lie or misrepresent information about your work.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check the content of your application.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>LaTeX for economics</title><link>https://pblanchenay.github.io/latex/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pblanchenay.github.io/latex/</guid><description>&lt;p>All of the codes below require the TikZ and pgfplots packages. Some also require GNUPLOT.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="plot-arbitrary-utility-function-in-3d-and-its-indifference-curves">Plot arbitrary utility function in 3D and its indifference curves&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Requires GNUPLOT. User can set utility function, and utility levels.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="UtilityFunction3D_IndiffCurves.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="UtilityFunction3D_IndiffCurves.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]
&lt;img src="UtilityFunction3D_IndiffCurves.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="indifference-curves-for-an-arbitrary-utility-function">Indifference curves for an arbitrary utility function&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Requires GNUPLOT. User can set utility function, and utility levels.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="AnyIndiffCurves.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="AnyIndiffCurves.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]
&lt;img src="AnyIndiffCurves.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="decomposing-a-price-change-into-income-and-substitution-effects">Decomposing a price change into income and substitution effects&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Requires GNUPLOT. Arbitrary utility function, but optimal choices must be comptued manually.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="IncomeSubstEffects.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="IncomeSubstEffects.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]
&lt;img src="IncomeSubstEffects.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="compensated-and-uncompensated-demands">Compensated and uncompensated demands&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Compensated and uncompensated demand functions must be computed manually. Intersections are computed automatically. Numerical values must be computed manually.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="Comp_Uncomp_Demands.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="Comp_Uncomp_Demands.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]
&lt;img src="Comp_Uncomp_Demands.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="long-run-and-short-run-equilibria-following-change-in-demand">Long-run and short-run equilibria following change in demand&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>User supplies marginal and average cost functions, and demands. The rest is computed automatically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="LRvsSRequil.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="LRvsSRequil.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]
&lt;img src="LRvsSRequil.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="consumer-surplus-producer-surplus-and-deadweight-loss-under-a-price-floor">Consumer surplus, producer surplus, and deadweight loss under a price floor&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>User supplies arbitrary demand and supply functions, and the price floor, higher than the original equilibrium price. The rest is computed automatically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="CS_PS_DWL_pricefloor.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="CS_PS_DWL_pricefloor.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]
&lt;img src="CS_PS_DWL_pricefloor.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="edgeworth-box">Edgeworth Box&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Requires GNUPLOT. User supplies arbitrary utility functions, and points where the indifference curves should intersect, and the contract curve. The rest is computed automatically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="EdgeworthContractCurve.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="EdgeworthContractCurve.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]
&lt;img src="EdgeworthContractCurve.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hypothesis-testing-of-a-single-proportion">Hypothesis testing (of a single proportion)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Distribution under the alternative hypothesis, and power/TypeII error, can be toggled on or off.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Code: &lt;a href="HypTestingSingleProportion.tex">TeX&lt;/a>]
[Result: &lt;a href="HypTestingSingleProportion.pdf">PDF&lt;/a>]&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="HypTestingSingleProportion.png" alt="This is an image">&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>